PART 3

We have already used the Raspberry Pi GPIO outputs to drive light emitting diodes, but it is
not possible to directly drive anything larger because of power limitations. In this part we
look at using a transistor to control devices that require more power.

So what do we mean when we talk about the
Raspberry Pi GPIO ports being low powered?
Power is measured in Watts and is calculated
from the available Voltage multiplied by the
available current. By default the Raspberry Pi
GPIO provides an output of 3.3 Volts and up
to 8 milliamperes. This means that our available
power output is limited to 3.3V x 0.008A
= 0.0264W or 26 milliwatts. While it is possible
to increase the output current to 16mA using a
software setting this still only gives us an absolute
maximum of 0.05W for a single GPIO pin,
it is however not advisable to run at this level
for any sustained period of time especially if
multiple IOs are in use. So I would advise you
to consider the default values the maximum.

26mW is a tiny amount of power that is inadequate
for the requirements of higher powered
devices such as motors and filament lamps
that typically have multi-watt power requirements.
However, it is possible to use the outputs
to act as control signals for electronically
activated switches, making it possible to control
virtually anything with the right equipment.
There are a number of different components
that can be used as power switching devices,
the one chosen will depend on the application
and equipment to be controlled.

The Transistor

We are going to be looking at a low power
transistor switching circuit. With the vast number
of transistors available from an electronics
catalogue you may be thinking that they
are complicated. However transistors can be
used in two ways, either as an amplifier or as
a switching device. For our purposes, using
them as an electronic switch simplifies things.

A transistor has three terminals called Collector,
Base & Emitter. When a small current is
applied to the Base terminal it allows a much
larger current to pass between the collector
and emitter terminals.

The amount of current that can be switched
depends on the transistor chosen and the
amount of current available to the base terminal.
This is known as the DC current gain
shown as hFE in a transistor data sheet. For
the PN2222A transistor the hFE Value is 100,
to switch a 150mA load we need only apply
1.5mA to the base, well within the capability of
the Raspberry Pi GPIO and gives us the ability
to switch up to 0.5W.

A typical transistor is a relatively low powered
device that on its own could not be used for
example to switch a 50W car headlamp but
could easily switch a bank of high brightness
LEDs or a small buzzer.

Transistors can only be used for DC Voltages,
so can NOT be used for switching AC mains
electricity. A key advantage of a transistor
is that it as it has no moving parts it can be
switched very quickly, thousands of times a
second if required and has a very long operational
life compared to a mechanical relay.

Alarm System Circuit
To demonstrate the use of a transistor, we will
construct an alarm system that will sound a
small buzzer when activated.
Circuit Description
We will be using two outputs and two inputs.
The first output is the familiar LED circuit that
will be used to indicate when the alarm is
armed. The second output is connected via resistor
R2 to the base of the transistor, the resistor
is necessary to limit the amount of current
supplied to the base of the transistor so that
there is just enough to switch it on. The collector
of the transistor is connected to a buzzer so
that it will sound when the output connected to
the base of the transistor is set high. Although
we could use the transistor to switch a higher
voltage for example 5V, to keep things simple
we are using a 3.3V buzzer so that the whole circuit can be powered from a single voltage.
The first input is the same small push-button
switch as in previous experiments, this will be
used to arm and disarm the alarm. The second
input is a magnetically operated reed switch.
A magnet would be attached to a door and
the switch to the door frame so that the switch
will be opened and closed when the door is
opened and closed. If you don’t intend to use
the circuit on a real door and prefer not to buy
a reed switch for the purpose of experimenting feel free to modify the circuit slightly to use
another small tactile switch or whatever sort of
switch you have to hand in place of the reed
switch.

The buzzer and transistor must be inserted
into the breadboard the correct way round.
The buzzer used here has a longer leg that
indicates the positive terminal that should be
connected to the top. The transistor should be
placed with the front (flat side) facing towards
the bottom of the breadboard as shown in the
illustration, the legs will need to be spread out
to fit the holes in the breadboard.

Program Description

The main loop of the program waits for GPIO
Pin 11 to go LOW when the button is pressed.
We then check to see if the door is closed by
checking the status of the reed switch on pin
13. If the door is open we briefly turn on the
buzzer to create a short beep and flash the
LED to indicate that we cannot arm the alarm.
Then we return to the main loop waiting for the
button to be pressed again.

If the door is closed we turn the LED on and
start a loop that constantly monitors the status
of the switches. If the push-button is pressed
we end the monitoring loop, switching off the
LED and returning to the main loop waiting
for the alarm to be armed again. If however
the reed switch is triggered by the door being
opened we sound the buzzer and flash the
LED. To avoid causing a nuisance with the
buzzer it will stop after 10 seconds but the LED
will remain flashing to show that the alarm was
set-off until the button is pressed again to reset
it. NOTE: You will need to press and hold the
button to reset the alarm after activation.

Conclusion
We have covered how to control high power
devices using a transistor. There are many
other options available for switching higher
power loads such as adding a second ‘Power
Transistor’ to the circuit to create what is known
as a darlington pair. Unfortunately there is not
enough space in this section to cover darlington
pairs and other switching methods.
If you have questions or ideas I would encourage
you to get involved on the official Raspberry
Pi forum to share ideas with others about
your projects. ●

Shopping List
COMPONENTS
1x 3mm Red LED (standard brightness)
1x 470Ω Resistor
3x 1kΩ Resistor
2x 10kΩ Resistor
1x Miniature PCB Tactile Switch
1x Reed Switch + Magnet
1x 3.3V Mini Buzzer
1x 2N2222 Transistor
ACCESSORIES
1x Breadboard
6x Male-female jumper wires
1x Selection of short jumper wires
TOOLS
If you don’t have them already then a set
of small long nosed pliers for bending
component leads and wire cutters will
make construction easier.

This article is sponsored by Tandy.
All the components mentioned in this series and much more
are available from the Tandy online shop.
http://www.tandyonline.co.uk/incontrol.html